<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<mediawiki xmlns:ns1="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11.xsd" version="0.11" xml:lang="en">
  <ns1:siteinfo>
    <ns1:sitename>Lustre Wiki</ns1:sitename>
    <ns1:dbname>wiki_lustre_org</ns1:dbname>
    <ns1:base>http://wiki.lustre.org/Main_Page</ns1:base>
    <ns1:generator>MediaWiki 1.39.7</ns1:generator>
    <ns1:case>first-letter</ns1:case>
    <ns1:namespaces>
      <ns1:namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</ns1:namespace>
      <ns1:namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</ns1:namespace>
      <ns1:namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <ns1:namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</ns1:namespace>
      <ns1:namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</ns1:namespace>
      <ns1:namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</ns1:namespace>
      <ns1:namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Lustre Wiki</ns1:namespace>
      <ns1:namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Lustre Wiki talk</ns1:namespace>
      <ns1:namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</ns1:namespace>
      <ns1:namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</ns1:namespace>
      <ns1:namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</ns1:namespace>
      <ns1:namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</ns1:namespace>
      <ns1:namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</ns1:namespace>
      <ns1:namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</ns1:namespace>
      <ns1:namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</ns1:namespace>
      <ns1:namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</ns1:namespace>
      <ns1:namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</ns1:namespace>
      <ns1:namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</ns1:namespace>
    </ns1:namespaces>
  </ns1:siteinfo>
  <ns1:page>
    <ns1:title>Infiniband Configuration Howto</ns1:title>
    <ns1:ns>0</ns1:ns>
    <ns1:id>724</ns1:id>
    <ns1:revision>
      <ns1:id>3929</ns1:id>
      <ns1:parentid>1667</ns1:parentid>
      <ns1:timestamp>2020-11-13T22:51:01Z</ns1:timestamp>
      <ns1:contributor>
        <ns1:username>Adilger</ns1:username>
        <ns1:id>8</ns1:id>
      </ns1:contributor>
      <ns1:minor />
      <ns1:comment>fix spelling, URL</ns1:comment>
      <ns1:origin>3929</ns1:origin>
      <ns1:model>wikitext</ns1:model>
      <ns1:format>text/x-wiki</ns1:format>
      <ns1:text bytes="3902" sha1="2o5hmufzuncglhu3pzrbysorlu03jo7" xml:space="preserve">== Introduction ==

This howto covers what is needed to handle working with varying different levels
of functionality of the InfiniBand stack. Like Lustre the InfiniBand software
stack has been under going large internal API changes and the impact of those
changes on the different InfiniBand hardware drivers have varied. Several
different API's have appeared in the InfiniBand layer. Previously lustre supported
two of those APIs called PMR and FMR. In the more recent kernel versions and
the external InfiniBand stacks available the PMR functionality was removed
leaving only FMR and the Fast Registration API remaining. Further plans exist to
eventually remove FMR support in only then leaves the Fast Registration API
remaining. With the plan of FMR removal in the future some of the InfiniBand
drivers only support the Fast Registration API. 

=== Lustre support ===
Code has been developed and merged to Lustre 2.9 to handle all these various cases 
just described. That work has been back ported to Lustre 2.8 but to date has not been
merged. If you are planning on running 2.8.0 and have a InfiniBand fabric that contains
different flavors of hardware that behave differently then you will need to for now 
download three different patches to apply them to the Lustre 2.8 source tree. They are:

&lt;br&gt;http://review.whamcloud.com/#/c/17606
&lt;br&gt;http://review.whamcloud.com/#/c/18347
&lt;br&gt;http://review.whamcloud.com/#/c/16367

=== Mellanox Hardware ===

One of the more common cases sites are running into is having different
types of Mellanox hardware in the same network. Currently some Mellanox
hardware requires running the mlx4 kernel driver and newer pieces of
hardware will depend on the mlx5 kernel driver. Each driver has very
different capabilities and to make these drivers communicate on the
Lustre level requires some tuning. The first difference you will notice
with the mlx5 kernel driver is that the largest value the peer credits
for the ko2iblnd driver can be set to is 16. This is due to the queue
pair depth being smaller for the mlx5 kernel driver when compared to
the mlx4 kernel driver. Original a limitation for Lustre was that the
peer credits for all pieces of InfiniBand hardware had to be the same
in value. Today this is not the case. Unfortunately, you will find that
even with Lustre support of different peer credits that if mlx4
hardware attempts to communicate with mlx5 hardware will fail. The
resolution to this problem was to determine what besides peer credits
influence the queue pair depth. That turned out to be the map on
demand feature of the `ko2iblnd` driver. By default the map on demand
feature is turned off by can be easily enabled. In my testing just
setting it to 256 which is the default if enabled allowed my mlx4
hardware to communicate with the mlx5 based devices. The work
done for [https://jira.whamcloud.com/browse/LU-7101 LU-7101]
also enabled configuring this setup with DLC
besides the traditional setting in the lnet module configuration
file. Included here is a example of an DLC configuration needed
for the mlx5 hardware. The section of interest if the LND tunables
section.

net:
    - net: lo
      nid: 0@lo
      status: up
      tunables:
          peer_timeout: 0
          peer_credits: 0
          peer_buffer_credits: 0
          credits: 0
    - net: o2ib1
      nid: 10.0.0.1@o2ib1
      status: up
      interfaces:
          0: ib0
      tunables:
          peer_timeout: 100
          peer_credits: 16
          peer_buffer_credits: 0
          credits: 2560
          CPT: "[0,0]"
      LND tunables:
          peercredits_hiw: 31
          map_on_demand: 256
          concurrent_sends: 63
          fmr_pool_size: 1280
          fmr_flush_trigger: 1024
          fmr_cache: 1

Once set up you should see success when bringing up your LNet interfaces.

[[Category:Router]][[Category:Administration]][[Category:LNET]]</ns1:text>
      <ns1:sha1>2o5hmufzuncglhu3pzrbysorlu03jo7</ns1:sha1>
    </ns1:revision>
  </ns1:page>
</mediawiki>