<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<mediawiki xmlns:ns1="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11.xsd" version="0.11" xml:lang="en">
  <ns1:siteinfo>
    <ns1:sitename>Lustre Wiki</ns1:sitename>
    <ns1:dbname>wiki_lustre_org</ns1:dbname>
    <ns1:base>http://wiki.lustre.org/Main_Page</ns1:base>
    <ns1:generator>MediaWiki 1.39.7</ns1:generator>
    <ns1:case>first-letter</ns1:case>
    <ns1:namespaces>
      <ns1:namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</ns1:namespace>
      <ns1:namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</ns1:namespace>
      <ns1:namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <ns1:namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</ns1:namespace>
      <ns1:namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</ns1:namespace>
      <ns1:namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</ns1:namespace>
      <ns1:namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Lustre Wiki</ns1:namespace>
      <ns1:namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Lustre Wiki talk</ns1:namespace>
      <ns1:namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</ns1:namespace>
      <ns1:namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</ns1:namespace>
      <ns1:namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</ns1:namespace>
      <ns1:namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</ns1:namespace>
      <ns1:namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</ns1:namespace>
      <ns1:namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</ns1:namespace>
      <ns1:namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</ns1:namespace>
      <ns1:namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</ns1:namespace>
      <ns1:namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</ns1:namespace>
      <ns1:namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</ns1:namespace>
    </ns1:namespaces>
  </ns1:siteinfo>
  <ns1:page>
    <ns1:title>Lustre User Group 2006</ns1:title>
    <ns1:ns>0</ns1:ns>
    <ns1:id>476</ns1:id>
    <ns1:revision>
      <ns1:id>5388</ns1:id>
      <ns1:parentid>5387</ns1:parentid>
      <ns1:timestamp>2026-01-12T19:05:54Z</ns1:timestamp>
      <ns1:contributor>
        <ns1:username>Adilger</ns1:username>
        <ns1:id>8</ns1:id>
      </ns1:contributor>
      <ns1:minor />
      <ns1:origin>5388</ns1:origin>
      <ns1:model>wikitext</ns1:model>
      <ns1:format>text/x-wiki</ns1:format>
      <ns1:text bytes="6666" sha1="q0n11rvv2evjlyr3xr9rjve5sbjabwc" xml:space="preserve">__TOC__
The fourth annual Lustre User Group Spring meeting was held April 18-20, 2006 on Hilton Head Island, SC.

The Lustre User Group was founded by Pacific Northwest National Laboratory and Lawrence Livermore National Laboratory to promote the use of the open source Lustre file system for HPC and scalable I/O. The annual meeting is an opportunity for current and prospective Lustre users to share and develop best practices, provide direct feedback to the Lustre development team, and receive an update on our plans for the coming year.

--------------------------------------------------------------------------------

==LUG 2006 Conference Schedule==
The target attendees for this meeting are users or administrators of a Lustre file system, and partners/resellers with Lustre offerings. Developers or researchers working with Lustre are also welcome, but should note that there is little content specifically for developers.

To allow for requested topics and submitted presentations, the agenda has several open slots. Please let us know what you would like to see in the program, and we'll do our best to accommodate the most popular requests.

If you would like to make a presentation at the meeting, please send a short proposal to lustre2006-submissions@clusterfs.com. This e-mail address is being protected from spam bots, you need JavaScript enabled to view it. Due to limited availability, please limit your presentation to topics of general interest such as best practices, lessons learned, research projects based on Lustre, or similar. Please do not submit sales presentations, and please submit before March 24.

The last two half-day sessions will provide a structured, organized forum for identifying and clarifying Lustre's future requirements. The goals are to gather input from customers and partners, identify conflicting requirements, and prioritize the rest. This replaces the half-day group discussions of the previous two LUG meetings.

While everyone is welcome to attend the first 1.5 days of the meeting, we must ask that organizations designate no more than two representatives for the Lustre Requirements Forum. These individuals are historically the liaisons from strategic Lustre partners and users who can speak to their organizations' requirements. To help us get an accurate count, please indicate on the registration form whether you will attend the Lustre Requirements Forum.

===Tuesday April 18, 2006=== 

9:00-9:30 a.m.  Welcome &amp; Introduction
Dr.Peter Braam - President &amp; CEO  

9:30-10:00 a.m.  [[Media:Lug_06_cfs_business_overview.pdf|Business Overview]] 
Jeffrey Denworth - Director of Sales 
 
10:00-10:30 a.m.  [[Media:Lug-supportpresentation-060418.pdf|Support &amp; QA Update]]
Peter Bojanic - Director of Engineering 
 
10:30-11:00 a.m.  Break 

11:00-12:00 a.m.  Lustre now and future:
architecture &amp; roadmap 

12:00-1:00 p.m.  Lunch 

1:00-1:30 p.m.  Lustre now and future:
architecture &amp; roadmap 

1:30-2:00 p.m.  Experiences with Lustre in a Seismic Processing Environment 
Chevron Corporation
 
2:00-2:30 p.m.  [[Media:Lug06-osu.pdf|Evaluating Lustre on DDR &amp; SDR Infiniband]]
Dr.DK Panda - Ohio State University
 
3:00-3:30 p.m.  Break 

3:30-3:45 p.m. [[Media:Lug06-ncsa.pdf|Lustre - WAN Update]]
Chris Cribbs - NCSA 

3:45-4:10 p.m.  CEA TERA10 100GB/s + Lustre Deployment 
Stephane Thiell - CEA DAM
 
4:10-4:30 p.m.  [[Media:Lug06-bull.pdf|Bull Lustre Management Tools for Large Clusters]]
Johann Lombardi - Bull
 
6:00-9:00 p.m. Lustre Users Reception

===Wednesday April 19, 2006 ===

9:00-9:30 a.m.  [[Media:Lug06-liquid.pdf|Converged Communications Systems Parallel File Systems and Copious IO]]
Jose Miguel Peleato - Liquid 

9:30-10:00 a.m.  [[Media:Lug06-hp.pdf|Key Issues Deploying Lustre at HP Customer Sites]]
Fergal Mc Carthy - HP
 
10:00-10:30 a.m.  Indiana University's Data Capacitor 
Steve Simms - Indiana University 

10:30-11:00 a.m.  Break 

11:00-11:30 a.m.  Cray Experiences Deploying Terascale Lustre Environments
Peter Rigsbee - Cray 

11:30-12:00 a.m.  [[Media:Lug06-ddn.pdf|Storage HW and Petascale I/O]]
Dave Fellinger - DataDirect Networks 

12:00-1:00 p.m.  Lunch 

1:00-5:00 p.m.  

Lustre Requirements Forum

-Requirements Survey

-Prioritization

-Refinement of Specific Requirements

-Break

-Implementation Scenarios

-Review

===Thursday April 20, 2006 ===

9:00-12:00 a.m.  

Lustre Requirements Forum

-Requirements Survey

-Prioritization

-Refinement of Specific Requirements

-Break

-Implementation Scenarios

-Review 

--------------------------------------------------------------------------------

==Registration==
Registration is open to all, however attendance is limited so please register early. While the registration deadline was Friday March 24, 2006, we will continue to accept registrations until the conference is full - however, we can no longer guarantee accommodations.

There is a conference fee of US$300 to cover the costs of hosting the meeting. Payments may be made by purchase order, credit card (all major cards accepted through Paypal), money order, or check.



-------------------------------------------------------------------------------

==Location, Travel, and Hotel==
The meeting will be held at [http://www.starwoodhotels.com/westin/property/overview/index.html?propertyID=1050 The Westin Resort, Hilton Head Island], 3 miles from the Hilton Head Island Airport (HHH) and about 45 miles from Savannah International Airport (SAV). We have negotiated a special group rate of $199/night, and reserved a block of rooms for our attendees. In addition, there is a reserved block of Government Per Diem rate rooms at $112/night.
Rooms must be booked before March 24, 2006 to take advantage of this group rate.
We are in the process of completing the reservation arrangements; please check back on February 14 for details about how to book these discounted rooms.

-------------------------------------------------------------------------------

==Contact==
To submit a presentation proposal, please send email to lustre2006-submissions@clusterfs.com. This e-mail address is being protected from spam bots, you need JavaScript enabled to view it .
For all other questions and comments related to the meeting, please send email to lustre2006@clusterfs.com. This e-mail address is being protected from spam bots, you need JavaScript enabled to view it .

* LUG Requirements Forum - [[Media:LUG-Requirements-060420-final.pdf|LUG-Requirements-060420-final.pdf]] | [http://wiki.lustre.org/images/7/78/LUG-Requirements-060420-final.xls LUG-Requirements-060420-final.xls]

[[Lustre User Group 2007|LUG'07 -&gt;]]

[[Category: LUG]]
[[Category: Events]]</ns1:text>
      <ns1:sha1>q0n11rvv2evjlyr3xr9rjve5sbjabwc</ns1:sha1>
    </ns1:revision>
  </ns1:page>
</mediawiki>