<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<mediawiki xmlns:ns1="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11.xsd" version="0.11" xml:lang="en">
  <ns1:siteinfo>
    <ns1:sitename>Lustre Wiki</ns1:sitename>
    <ns1:dbname>wiki_lustre_org</ns1:dbname>
    <ns1:base>http://wiki.lustre.org/Main_Page</ns1:base>
    <ns1:generator>MediaWiki 1.39.7</ns1:generator>
    <ns1:case>first-letter</ns1:case>
    <ns1:namespaces>
      <ns1:namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</ns1:namespace>
      <ns1:namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</ns1:namespace>
      <ns1:namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <ns1:namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</ns1:namespace>
      <ns1:namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</ns1:namespace>
      <ns1:namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</ns1:namespace>
      <ns1:namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Lustre Wiki</ns1:namespace>
      <ns1:namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Lustre Wiki talk</ns1:namespace>
      <ns1:namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</ns1:namespace>
      <ns1:namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</ns1:namespace>
      <ns1:namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</ns1:namespace>
      <ns1:namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</ns1:namespace>
      <ns1:namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</ns1:namespace>
      <ns1:namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</ns1:namespace>
      <ns1:namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</ns1:namespace>
      <ns1:namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</ns1:namespace>
      <ns1:namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</ns1:namespace>
      <ns1:namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</ns1:namespace>
    </ns1:namespaces>
  </ns1:siteinfo>
  <ns1:page>
    <ns1:title>Lustre Upstreaming to Linux Kernel</ns1:title>
    <ns1:ns>0</ns1:ns>
    <ns1:id>664</ns1:id>
    <ns1:revision>
      <ns1:id>5416</ns1:id>
      <ns1:parentid>5404</ns1:parentid>
      <ns1:timestamp>2026-02-24T16:35:41Z</ns1:timestamp>
      <ns1:contributor>
        <ns1:username>Tim-day-387</ns1:username>
        <ns1:id>152</ns1:id>
      </ns1:contributor>
      <ns1:origin>5416</ns1:origin>
      <ns1:model>wikitext</ns1:model>
      <ns1:format>text/x-wiki</ns1:format>
      <ns1:text bytes="13436" sha1="2n6my71wk74fb3jumlcnxfg8s9mtlkg" xml:space="preserve">The Lustre upstreaming effort is currently being managed as part of the &lt;code&gt;master&lt;/code&gt; Lustre development branch, and submitted patches should follow the normal Lustre patch submission process, which includes fixing issues reported by checkpatch.pl, so that the code follows the upstream kernel style guidelines.  Once all issues in the Lustre code that are known to be blocking upstream submission have been addressed, then the filesystem will be resubmitted to the upstream kernel.

== Pending Work ==

Significant work has gone into improving the Lustre codebase since the Lustre client was removed from staging. Below are listed some of the major areas of ongoing work. This list is not comprehensive. The first ticket &lt;code&gt;LU-12511&lt;/code&gt; links to a lot of work that has been completed historically. This table will be updated periodically as new requirements emerge and as work becomes completed.

{| class="wikitable sortable"

|-
! Task !! Status !! Notes !! Jira !! Patch(es)
|-

|-
| Prepare Lustre for Adoption in the Linux kernel || Incomplete || This is the main Jira ticket - which links to other subtasks || [https://jira.whamcloud.com/browse/LU-12511 LU-12511] || Various
|-

|-
| IPv6 Support || Complete || Initial support in 2.16, finalized support in 2.17 || [https://jira.whamcloud.com/browse/LU-18417 LU-18417] || Various
|-

|-
| Enforce Linux kernel coding style || Mostly Complete || The majority of checkpatch.pl warnings have been addressed. We hope to get the baseline for Lustre similar to other in-tree filesystems. || [https://jira.whamcloud.com/browse/LU-6142 LU-6142] || Various
|-

|-
| Convert to kernel-doc comments || Partially Complete || Work is currently underway. || [https://jira.whamcloud.com/browse/LU-9633 LU-9633] || Various
|-

|-
| Unify Lustre kernel modules || Incomplete || Reduce the total number of Lustre kernel modules || [https://jira.whamcloud.com/browse/LU-17862 LU-17862] || [https://review.whamcloud.com/c/fs/lustre-release/+/55153 55153]
|-

|-
| Split userspace, compat, and kernel code || Mostly Complete || Split the core filesystem from the compatibility code needed to support older kernels || [https://jira.whamcloud.com/browse/LU-18687 LU-18687] || Various
|-

|-
| Replace libcfs hashing code with rhashtable || Incomplete || Most of the users on the client have been removed; the majority of the work is server-side || [https://jira.whamcloud.com/browse/LU-8130 LU-8130] || Various
|-

|-
| Adapt Lustre Infiniband driver to latest APIs || Incomplete || This is pending the transition to p2pdma API || [https://jira.whamcloud.com/browse/LU-8874 LU-8874] || Various
|-

|-
| Remove ProcFS users || Incomplete || Most of the users on the client have been removed; the majority of the work is server-side || [https://jira.whamcloud.com/browse/LU-8066 LU-8066] || Various
|-

|-
| Remove custom interval-tree || Complete || - || [https://jira.whamcloud.com/browse/LU-11085 LU-11085] || Various
|-

|-
| Transition completely to folios || Incomplete || A lot of callbacks have been implemented; still have dependency on mm/folio-compat.c; large folio support is in-flight || [https://jira.whamcloud.com/browse/LU-17916 LU-17916] || Various
|-

|-
| -&gt;writepage could likely be deprecated || Incomplete || Mostly a factor of ensure Lustre still behaves - [https://lwn.net/Articles/893512/ context] || [https://jira.whamcloud.com/browse/LU-18675 LU-18675] || [https://review.whamcloud.com/c/fs/lustre-release/+/57894 57894]
|-

|-
| Transition to p2pdma || Incomplete || Lustre should use upstream p2pdma framework rather than interfacing with out-of-tree modules || [https://jira.whamcloud.com/browse/LU-19848 LU-19848] || Various
|-

|-
| Don't use Autotools for kernel modules || Mostly Complete || Lustre kernel modules should not be built with Autotools || [https://jira.whamcloud.com/browse/LU-18876 LU-18876] || Various
|-

|-
| Don't use inline #ifdef for kernel compatibility || Incomplete || The core Lustre kernel docs should be free from extraneous #ifdefs || - || Various
|-

|-
| Ensure that Lustre builds on all support architectures || Incomplete || - || - || Various
|-

|-
| Ensure Lustre can build !MODULE || Mostly Complete || Fix bugs when building Lustre into the kernel image || [https://jira.whamcloud.com/browse/LU-19874 LU-19874] || Various
|-

|}

== Proposed Transition to an Upstream-first Development Model ==

[[Image:Split_lustre_tree.png]]

==== Background ====

Currently, the Lustre kernel modules are maintained as an out-of-tree driver. This driver supports a variety of vendor kernels (primarily on RHEL and Ubuntu). Code is developed first for these vendors kernels. It is later updated to support newer kernel as they are release. The core filesystem code and the compatibility code are intermixed.

For upstreaming to work, the normal development flow has to generate patches to mainline Linux. However, we must still support the older distribution kernels that most people use to run Lustre. To achieve this - we must invert the development model. Code must be developed first for the upstream kernel. Afterwards, this code will be supported on older kernels via a compatibility layer maintained by the Lustre development community. These next sections provide a high-level overview and defines a clear roadmap with tangible milestones on our path to upstream. This transition will occur in stages and will proceed in parallel with normal development - without interrupting normal feature work.

The timelines provided are approximate.

==== Tenets ====

There are several important considerations we must account for when undertaking this work (in order of importance):

* '''Mainline Linux is the source of truth''' - Every Lustre release must be derived from a mainline Linux release. Code change to Lustre should target mainline Linux first - and later be backported as needed. We should not block upstream improvements to facilitate backporting.

* '''Do not complicate the process of contributing to Lustre''' - Lustre has an active developer community and a large amount of pre-existing test infrastructure. Our existing processes have worked well. We should maintain the beneficial aspects of our existing workflows while transitioning to an upstream-first model.

* '''Integrate with the wider filesystem community''' - We should strive to share Lustre's improvements and advancements with the wider filesystem community. We should regularly collaborate with others in the community to facilitate kernel-wide improvements.

==== [I] Separate the kernel code, compatibility code, and userspace code ====

'''''ETA: June 2025'''''

The Lustre tree should be reorganized to have a clear separation of concerns:

&lt;pre&gt;
lustre/            -&gt; Lustre filesystem kernel modules
lnet/              -&gt; Lustre Networking kernel modules
lnet/debug/        -&gt; Lustre debugging code
lustre_compat/     -&gt; Kernel backwards compatibility code
tests/             -&gt; Regression tests
utils/             -&gt; Userspace tools
&lt;/pre&gt;

The functional components of &lt;code&gt;libcfs/&lt;/code&gt; will be split into &lt;code&gt;lustre/&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;lnet/&lt;/code&gt;, and &lt;code&gt;debug/&lt;/code&gt;. The kernel backwards compatibility components would live in &lt;code&gt;lustre_compat/&lt;/code&gt;. Centralizing the compatibility code makes it easier to maintain and update and allows us to start removing the compatibility code (and #ifdefs) from the modules themselves. &lt;code&gt;lustre_compat/&lt;/code&gt; will be compiled into &lt;code&gt;libcfs.ko&lt;/code&gt;. The debugging code in &lt;code&gt;debug/&lt;/code&gt; will be compiled into &lt;code&gt;lnet.ko&lt;/code&gt; (or perhaps a standalone module).

The compatibility code will provide interfaces that mirror the upstream kernel-tree. After a new upstream kernel (with Lustre included) is released, we will update the compatibility layer as-needed to support that release on older kernels. A user of Lustre could either use the upstream kernel
as-is with the in-tree Lustre modules - or they could compile and use those same modules on an LTS kernel release via the compatibility layer.

==== [II] Get lustre/ and lnet/ to natively compile on a mainline kernel ====

'''''ETA: April 2026'''''

Once the compatibility code is isolated, we must get &lt;code&gt;lustre/&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;lnet/&lt;/code&gt; to natively compile on a mainline kernel - without any Autotools magic, #ifdefs, or &lt;code&gt;lustre_compat/&lt;/code&gt; layer.

This would be enforced by adding build validation to each patch submitted to the Lustre Gerrit. The kernel version would be pinned in the Lustre build scripts and we'd periodically update it and fix any new build failures.

Once this is achieved, we'll have a clean, idiomatic, mainline Linux client and server that can be run on older distributions via a compatibility layer.

==== [III] Move lustre/ and lnet/ to a separate kernel tree ====

'''''ETA: February 2027''''' (This would immediately precede submission for inclusion) 

Transition to maintaining &lt;code&gt;lustre/&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;lnet/&lt;/code&gt; as a series on patches on top of a mainline kernel release. At this point, we'll generating patches to mainline Linux while retaining the ability to support older distro kernels via &lt;code&gt;lustre_compat/&lt;/code&gt;. Similar to the previous step, we periodically rebase our Lustre patch series - fixing &lt;code&gt;lustre_compat/&lt;/code&gt; as needed.

This is the only step that requires a significant change the Lustre development workflow - patches would have to be split and sent to two different repositories. This step will be delayed until we're ready to submit Lustre upstream.

==== [IV] Submit the patch series for inclusion ====

'''''ETA: February 2027'''''

Once we are comfortable with the above process, we can submit the initial patches to add Lustre support to the kernel. Our normal development flow will generate a batch of patches to be submitted during each merge window. After the merge window, we can focus on testing and making sure that our backport to older distro kernels is still functional.





== FAQ ==

; Who will actually run the Lustre code in mainline Linux?
: Everyone. Releases for older distros will be a combination of the upstream Lustre combined with &lt;code&gt;lustre_compat/&lt;/code&gt; and whatever stuff the kernel won't allow.

; What will a Lustre release look like?
: We can generate a tarball by combining an upstream Lustre release from mainline along with &lt;code&gt;lustre_compat/&lt;/code&gt; and the userspace stuff. Vendors and third-parties can base their versions of Lustre on those tarballs. Every time a new kernel releases - a new Lustre release tarball will be created. LTS releases can center around the LTS kernel releases.

; How will we validate that lustre/ and lnet/ build on mainline before upstream submission?
: A bot, [https://tim-day-387.github.io/upstream-patch-review/# ktest], will perform minimum build, boot, and mount testing for Lustre clients and servers on the latest mainline kernels. We will investigate integrating with [https://docs.kernelci.org/ KernelCI] in the future.

; Does anyone else have a similar model? Does this even work?
: DRBD was upstreamed previously and maintains an out-of-tree [https://github.com/LINBIT/drbd copy of this code] for support on LTS kernels. AMD GPU also seems to have a similar approach. We hope to talk to other developers working in a model similar to this.

&lt;br&gt;


== Testing ==

Currently, [https://tim-day-387.github.io/upstream-patch-review/# ktest] is used to validate that Lustre continues to build and run against the latest mainline kernels. In the future, it will validate various kernel configurations and architecture builds. It will also perform various static checks and validations.

Lustre also has extensive [https://build.whamcloud.com/ build] and [https://testing.whamcloud.com/test_sessions testing] against LTS kernels.

&lt;br&gt;


== Past Talks and Coverage ==

This section covers previous talks and coverage about the Lustre upstreaming process.

==== Lustre Administrators and Developers (LAD) ====

[https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Sjbpq73SoIE LAD 2022: Native Linux client Status - James Simmons]

[https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=g8xOy7HTo3w LAD 2020: Linux Lustre Client State - James Simmons]

==== Lustre User Group (LUG) ====

[https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=nOPpWygOreI LUG 2025: Lustre Upstreaming Efforts - James Simmons]

[https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=jPTGlazji3A&amp;t=1s LUG 2024: Native Linux client Status - James Simmons]

[https://vimeo.com/339571280 LUG 2019: Lustre - A view from the outside - Neil Brown]

==== LSF/MM/eBPF ====

[https://wiki.lustre.org/images/f/f9/LUG2025-Lustre_Upstream_Kernel_Client-Day.pdf Lustre Upstreaming]

==== Linux Weekly News (LWN) ====

[https://lwn.net/Articles/1025268/ Getting Lustre upstream]

[https://lwn.net/Articles/756565/ Will staging lose its Lustre?]

== Mailing List Archives ==

This is a collection of mailing list threads of interest - any useful discussion related to upstreaming Lustre.

[https://lore.kernel.org/linux-fsdevel/B588ECCE-7CBF-4111-841F-0510A8F5886B@amazon.com/T/#u Lustre Upstreaming Project Update (2026)]

[https://lore.kernel.org/linux-fsdevel/DA28F0FE-ACB6-486E-BF3D-85AF328FE2AD@amazon.com/T/#t LSF/MM (2025)]

[http://lists.lustre.org/pipermail/lustre-devel-lustre.org/2025-January/thread.html Discussing Lustre Upstreaming with Lustre Developers (2025)]

[https://lwn.net/ml/linux-fsdevel/20180601091133.GA27521@kroah.com/ Lustre removed from staging]</ns1:text>
      <ns1:sha1>2n6my71wk74fb3jumlcnxfg8s9mtlkg</ns1:sha1>
    </ns1:revision>
  </ns1:page>
</mediawiki>