<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<mediawiki xmlns:ns1="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11.xsd" version="0.11" xml:lang="en">
  <ns1:siteinfo>
    <ns1:sitename>Lustre Wiki</ns1:sitename>
    <ns1:dbname>wiki_lustre_org</ns1:dbname>
    <ns1:base>http://wiki.lustre.org/Main_Page</ns1:base>
    <ns1:generator>MediaWiki 1.39.7</ns1:generator>
    <ns1:case>first-letter</ns1:case>
    <ns1:namespaces>
      <ns1:namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</ns1:namespace>
      <ns1:namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</ns1:namespace>
      <ns1:namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <ns1:namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</ns1:namespace>
      <ns1:namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</ns1:namespace>
      <ns1:namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</ns1:namespace>
      <ns1:namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Lustre Wiki</ns1:namespace>
      <ns1:namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Lustre Wiki talk</ns1:namespace>
      <ns1:namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</ns1:namespace>
      <ns1:namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</ns1:namespace>
      <ns1:namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</ns1:namespace>
      <ns1:namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</ns1:namespace>
      <ns1:namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</ns1:namespace>
      <ns1:namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</ns1:namespace>
      <ns1:namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</ns1:namespace>
      <ns1:namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</ns1:namespace>
      <ns1:namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</ns1:namespace>
      <ns1:namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</ns1:namespace>
    </ns1:namespaces>
  </ns1:siteinfo>
  <ns1:page>
    <ns1:title>OBDFilter Survey</ns1:title>
    <ns1:ns>0</ns1:ns>
    <ns1:id>1143</ns1:id>
    <ns1:revision>
      <ns1:id>5033</ns1:id>
      <ns1:parentid>2482</ns1:parentid>
      <ns1:timestamp>2024-12-02T15:51:24Z</ns1:timestamp>
      <ns1:contributor>
        <ns1:username>Elliswilson</ns1:username>
        <ns1:id>140</ns1:id>
      </ns1:contributor>
      <ns1:comment>/* References */</ns1:comment>
      <ns1:origin>5033</ns1:origin>
      <ns1:model>wikitext</ns1:model>
      <ns1:format>text/x-wiki</ns1:format>
      <ns1:text bytes="11028" sha1="gfuuy27jnukldi2i3zsi0tke6i1p9o0" xml:space="preserve">== Description ==

OBDFilter-Survey tests the performance of one or more OSTs by simulating Lustre client IO. Each OSS server in an installation is tested individually. The &lt;code&gt;obdfilter-survey&lt;/code&gt; script is a wrapper around the &lt;code&gt;lctl&lt;/code&gt; sub-command &lt;code&gt;test_brw&lt;/code&gt;. OBDFilter-survey requires a functional Lustre file system, i.e. MGS and MDT running, target OSTs running. Lustre clients are not required for disk-only test but are needed for the network and remote file system (netdisk) modes (although in practice, the latter two modes are not used).

There are 3 test cases covered by the &lt;code&gt;obdfilter-survey&lt;/code&gt; benchmark, referred to as:

* &lt;code&gt;disk&lt;/code&gt;
* &lt;code&gt;network&lt;/code&gt;
* &lt;code&gt;netdisk&lt;/code&gt;

The &lt;code&gt; network&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;netdisk&lt;/code&gt; modes are not normally used for benchmarking as they may produce unreliable results. The &lt;code&gt;network&lt;/code&gt; test has been effectively superseded by the [[LNET_Selftest]] benchmark. Also note that the &lt;code&gt;obdfilter-survey&lt;/code&gt; benchmark itself does not scale well beyond a small number of OSTs. From the Lustre discussion mailing list:

&lt;blockquote style="font-style: italic; border-left: solid #ccc  2px; padding: 2px 7px 2px 7px;"&gt;
The obdfilter_survey script is NOT scalable beyond tens of OSTs since it is only intended to measure the I/O performance of individual storage subsystems, not the scalability of the entire system.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Therefore, only run &lt;code&gt;obdfilter-survey&lt;/code&gt; on individual OSTs, using the &lt;code&gt;disk&lt;/code&gt; test case.

'''Note:''' &lt;code&gt;obdfilter-survey&lt;/code&gt; is a potentially destructive test and there is a small risk that pre-existing data will be lost during execution.  The test will consume capacity on the storage targets during execution and, in the manner of all benchmarks, will compete with other processes for resources. Do not run this benchmark on a system containing production data.

== Purpose ==

OBDFilter-Survey provides feedback on the potential performance of OSTs attached to an OSS. The &lt;code&gt;obdfilter-survey&lt;/code&gt; script generates sequential I/O from varying numbers of threads and objects (files) to simulate the I/O patterns of a Lustre client. It can be run directly on an OSS node to measure the OST storage performance without any intervening network, or it can be run remotely on a Lustre client to measure the OST performance including network overhead.

The approach and methodology for &lt;code&gt;obdfilter-survey&lt;/code&gt; is very similar to that for [[SGPDD_Survey|sgpdd-survey]].

== Preparation ==

# Install the host operating system for each of the Lustre servers (MGS, MDS and OSS). On some sites, the MGS will be co-located with an MDS.
# Install the Lustre server software distribution on each system.
# Configure the Lustre Network (LNet) module and verify that it is operating correctly.
# Create the MGS, MDT and OST file system targets according to the system design.
# Start the Lustre services (mount MGS, OSTs and MDTs).

== Benchmark Execution ==

The &lt;code&gt;obdfilter-survey&lt;/code&gt; script takes its parameters from environment variables established at run time. The parameters that are of most interest are as follows (refer to the section [[#OBDFilter-Survey_Input_Parameters|OBDFilter-Survey Input Parameters]] for a detailed breakdown of the parameters and how to calculate suitable values):

{| border=1 cellpadding=5 style="border-collapse: collapse; border: solid 1px #ccc;"
|- style="text-align: left; vertical-align: bottom; background-color: #eee;"
! scope="col"| Name
! scope="col" style="width:50%" | Description
! scope="col"| Typical Values
|- style="text-align: left; vertical-align: top;"
! scope="row"| &lt;code&gt;nobjlo&lt;/code&gt;
| Initial object count
| &lt;code&gt;1&lt;/code&gt;
|- style="text-align: left; vertical-align: top;"
! scope="row"| &lt;code&gt;nobjhi&lt;/code&gt;
| Maximum object count
| &lt;code&gt;512&lt;/code&gt;
|- style="text-align: left; vertical-align: top;"
! scope="row"| &lt;code&gt;thrlo&lt;/code&gt;
| Initial number of threads
| &lt;code&gt;1&lt;/code&gt;
|- style="text-align: left; vertical-align: top;"
! scope="row"| &lt;code&gt;thrhi&lt;/code&gt;
| Maximum number of threads
| &lt;code&gt;1024&lt;/code&gt;
|- style="text-align: left; vertical-align: top;"
! scope="row"| &lt;code&gt;size&lt;/code&gt;
| Data set size in MiB per OST. Cannot exceed the capacity of an individual OST
| &lt;code&gt;2.5 * size(RAM) / count(LUNs)&lt;/code&gt;
|- style="text-align: left; vertical-align: top;"
! scope="row"| &lt;code&gt;rslt_loc&lt;/code&gt;
| Directory to contain results. Must exist before script is run
| &lt;code&gt;/var/tmp/obdfilter-survey_out&lt;/code&gt;
|- style="text-align: left; vertical-align: top;"
! scope="row"| &lt;code&gt;targets&lt;/code&gt;
| Space separated list of OSTs to test, enclosed in quotes. Each target is referenced using the object label, in the format &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;fsname&amp;gt;-OST&amp;lt;index&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;"
| &lt;code&gt;"lustre-OST0006 lustre-OST0007"&lt;/code&gt;
|-
|}

The following is an example command line for executing &lt;code&gt;obdfilter-survey&lt;/code&gt;:

&lt;pre style="overflow-x:auto;"&gt;
mkdir -p /var/tmp/obdfilter-survey_out

nobjlo=1 nobjhi=512 \
thrlo=1 thrhi=1024 \
size=51200 \
rslt_loc=/var/tmp/obdfilter-survey_out \
targets="lustre-OST0006 lustre-OST0007 lustre-OST0008" \
case=disk \
obdfilter-survey
&lt;/pre&gt;

== OBDFilter-Survey Input Parameters ==

'''Note:''' The parameters to &lt;code&gt;obdfilter-survey&lt;/code&gt; are largely undocumented. This section attempts to accurately reflect the intended meaning and usage of each parameter.

'''Note:''' Due to the similarity between &lt;code&gt;sgpdd-survey&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;obdfilter-survey&lt;/code&gt; command options, some material is duplicated between the two pages.

{| border=1 cellpadding=5 style="border-collapse: collapse; border: solid 1px #ccc;"
|- style="text-align: left; vertical-align: bottom; background-color: #eee;"
! scope="col"| Name
! scope="col" style="width:50%" | Description
! scope="col"| Typical Values
|- style="text-align: left; vertical-align: top;"
! scope="row"| &lt;code&gt;nobjlo&lt;/code&gt;

&lt;code&gt;nobjhi&lt;/code&gt;
| The number of concurrent objects to create on each iteration, per OST. Starting at &lt;code&gt;nobjlo&lt;/code&gt;, the number of objects is doubled on each iteration until &lt;code&gt;nobjhi&lt;/code&gt; is reached.

The &lt;code&gt;nobjlo&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;nobjhi&lt;/code&gt; parameters control how many independent objects on the OST will be read or written simultaneously. This is intended to simulate multiple Lustre clients accessing each OST.
| &lt;code&gt;nobjlo=1&lt;/code&gt;

&lt;code&gt;nobjhi=512&lt;/code&gt;
|- style="text-align: left; vertical-align: top;"
! scope="row"| &lt;code&gt;thrlo&lt;/code&gt;

&lt;code&gt;thrhi&lt;/code&gt;
| The range of threads to iterate over. The thread count is doubled on every iteration of the thread count loop. The &lt;code&gt;thrlo&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;thrhi&lt;/code&gt; parameters are used to direct the number of worker threads running in parallel. This is intended to simulate the Lustre OSS threads.
| &lt;code&gt;thrlo=1&lt;/code&gt;

&lt;code&gt;thrhi=1024&lt;/code&gt;
|- style="text-align: left; vertical-align: top;"
! scope="row"| &lt;code&gt;size&lt;/code&gt;
| The data set size in MiB per storage device (LUN). The total dataset size for the entire benchmark is calculated as the LUN dataset size multiplied by the number of LUNs in the benchmark:

&lt;pre style="overflow-x:auto;"&gt;
ds_total = size * count(LUNs)
&lt;/pre&gt;

Set &lt;code&gt;size&lt;/code&gt; to a small value (e.g. 100MB) to quickly test the configuration for correctness.

For a full benchmarking run, set &lt;code&gt;ds_total&lt;/code&gt; to a value greater than or equal to twice the target system's RAM. This circumvents any cacheing that may occur within the target system. From this, calculate the value of the &lt;code&gt;size&lt;/code&gt; input parameter for &lt;code&gt;obdfilter-survey&lt;/code&gt; as follows:

&lt;pre style="overflow-x:auto;"&gt;
size = ds_total / count(LUNs)
&lt;/pre&gt;
where &lt;code&gt;ds_total = 2.5 * RAM&lt;/code&gt;

As an example, for a server with 32GB RAM and 4 LUNs, the input size is calculated as follows:

&lt;pre style="overflow-x:auto;"&gt;
size = (32GB * 2.5) / 4 LUNs
     = (32768MiB * 2.5) / 4
     = 81920 / 4
     = 20480
&lt;/pre&gt;
| &lt;code&gt;2.5 * sizeof(RAM) / count(LUNs)&lt;/code&gt;

e.g.:

&lt;code&gt;size=20480&lt;/code&gt;
|- style="text-align: left; vertical-align: top;"
! scope="row"| &lt;code&gt;rslt_loc&lt;/code&gt;
| Directory to contain results. Must exist before benchmark is run. 
| &lt;code&gt;rslt_loc=/var/tmp/obdfilter-survey_out&lt;/code&gt;
|- style="text-align: left; vertical-align: top;"
! scope="row"| &lt;code&gt;rszlo&lt;/code&gt;

&lt;code&gt;rszhi&lt;/code&gt;
| The record size in KB. The default is for 1MB I/O, which mirrors Lustre's write size. Provided that these values are set to 1024 (i.e. 1MiB), there is no need to set them explicitly. This maps to the &lt;code&gt;bpt&lt;/code&gt; (blocks per transfer) parameter in &lt;code&gt;sgp_dd&lt;/code&gt;, referring to the number of blocks in each I/O transaction.
| 
|-
|}

== Issues ==
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If the test is aborted before completion, the target OST will not be cleaned up. Over time, the OST will fill with objects if this pattern of aborting runs is repeated. It is difficult to clean these objects from the OST. If this happens, umount the OST and re-mount as type &lt;code&gt;ldiskfs&lt;/code&gt;. Go to the &lt;code&gt;O/2&lt;/code&gt; (alphabetic letter capital 'O' – oh – ''not'' the numeral zero) directory and remove the objects found there. Do not remove the &lt;code&gt;LAST_ID&lt;/code&gt; file.

Alternatively, read the object IDs from the detail log of the test run and use the following command while the file system is mounted as type &lt;code&gt;lustre&lt;/code&gt;:

&lt;pre style="overflow-x:auto;"&gt;
lctl --device &lt;ostref&gt; destroy &lt;1st object&gt; &lt;count&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ERROR entries in the benchmark output usually mean out of space condition – check detail log.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;SHORT entries in the benchmark output usually mean test completed too quickly, e.g. because data size is too small – check detail log.&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;On catastrophic fail, echo-clients might not be cleaned up. Use &lt;code&gt;lctl&lt;/code&gt; to fix, e.g.:

&lt;pre style="overflow-x:auto;"&gt;
[root@oss1 ~]# lctl dl
0 UP mgc MGC10.73.0.11@tcp 82e16bb1-9e83-1236-4435-c0dcf29a04da 5
1 UP ost OSS OSS_uuid 3
2 UP obdfilter lustre-OST0000 lustre-OST0000_UUID 7
3 AT echo_client lustre-OST0000_ecc lustre-OST0000_ecc_UUID 1

[root@oss1 ~]# lctl
lctl &gt; cfg lustre-OST0000_ecc
lctl &gt; cleanup
lctl &gt; detach
lctl &gt; exit

[root@oss1 ~]# lctl dl
0 UP mgc MGC10.73.0.11@tcp 82e16bb1-9e83-1236-4435-c0dcf29a04da 5
1 UP ost OSS OSS_uuid 3
2 UP obdfilter lustre-OST0000 lustre-OST0000_UUID 7
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

== References ==

* [https://doc.lustre.org/lustre_manual.xhtml#benchmark.ost_perf Lustre manual: Testing OST Performance (obdfilter-survey)]

== Appendix: Sample &lt;code&gt;obdfilter-survey&lt;/code&gt; script ==

&lt;pre style="overflow-x:auto;"&gt;
#!/bin/bash
# Minimal obdfilter-survey script
TARGETS="oss01:lustre oss02:lustre1 oss02:lustre2"
NOBJLO=1
NOBJHI=1
THRLO=16
THRHI=16
OUTPUT="/tmp/obdfilter-survey-1j-16t-100s.out"
# SIZE="46000"
SIZE="100"
ssh oss01 mkdir -p $OUTPUT
ssh oss02 mkdir -p $OUTPUT
thrhi=$THRHI thrlo=$THRLO \
nobjhi=$NOBJHI nobjlo=$NOBJLO \
size=$SIZE case="disk" \
targets=$TARGETS rslt_loc=$OUTPUT \
/usr/bin/obdfilter-survey
&lt;/pre&gt;

[[Category:Benchmarking]]</ns1:text>
      <ns1:sha1>gfuuy27jnukldi2i3zsi0tke6i1p9o0</ns1:sha1>
    </ns1:revision>
  </ns1:page>
</mediawiki>